<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King Charles I, no such saint, martyr or good Protestant as commonly reputed, but a favourer of Papists and a cruel and oppressive tyrant all plainly proved from undeniable matters of fact : to which are added Dr. Burnet's, now Bishop of Salisbury, and other reasons, against the keeping up any longer the observation of a fast on the 30th of January : as also short answers to these three questions, I, what is the occasion of the clergies pride and lording it over the laity, II, why they and many of the laity cry up this king for a saint, martyr, &amp;c., III, what is the true reason that the generality of the clergy, and many of the laity, both lawyers and others, are constant advocates for kings, tho never so wicked, and sacrificers of the people.</title>
            <author>D. J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13652847</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13652847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King Charles I, no such saint, martyr or good Protestant as commonly reputed, but a favourer of Papists and a cruel and oppressive tyrant all plainly proved from undeniable matters of fact : to which are added Dr. Burnet's, now Bishop of Salisbury, and other reasons, against the keeping up any longer the observation of a fast on the 30th of January : as also short answers to these three questions, I, what is the occasion of the clergies pride and lording it over the laity, II, why they and many of the laity cry up this king for a saint, martyr, &amp;c., III, what is the true reason that the generality of the clergy, and many of the laity, both lawyers and others, are constant advocates for kings, tho never so wicked, and sacrificers of the people.</title>
                  <author>D. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: D.J.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>King Charles I. No ſuch SAINT, MARTYR, or GOOD PROTESTANT as commonly reputed; BUT A FAVOURER of PAPISTS, and a Cruel and Oppreſſive TYRANT.</p>
            <p>All plainly proved from undeniable Matters of Fact.</p>
            <p>To which are added Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s (now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) and other Reaſons, againſt the keeping up any longer the obſervation of a Faſt on the 30th of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO Short Anſwers to theſe three Queſtions. I. What is the Occaſion of the Clergies Pride and Lording it over the Laity? II. Why they, and many of the Laity, cry up this King for a Saint, Martyr? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> III. What is the true Reaſon that the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Clergy, and many of the Laity, both Lawyers and others, are conſtant Advocates for Kings (tho never ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) and Sacrificers of the People?</p>
            <q>
               <p>He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. 23.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Ahab,</hi> the Son of <hi>Omri,</hi> did evil in the ſight of the Lord, above all that were before him.
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Kings 30.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>And hath deſpiſed, in the indignation of his anger, the KING and the Prieſt.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Lam. 2.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, that the Lord ſhall puniſh the hoſt of the high ones that are on high, and the Kings of the earth, that are on the earth.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 24.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>And I will come upon him while he is weary and weakhanded, and will make him afraid, and all the people that are with him ſhall flee; and I will SMITE the KING ONLY.
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. 17.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind was hardned with Pride, he was <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed from his Kingly Throne,</hi> and they <hi>took his Glory</hi> from <hi>him.</hi>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Dan. 5.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or this <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> Priest of the moſt high God, who met <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> returning from the Slaughter of Kings, and bleſſed him.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 7.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the 10th Year of our Redemption from Popery and Slavery. 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100997:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100997:2"/>
            <head>To the good People of <hi>England,</hi> who ſincerely love and will maintain the <hi>Proteſtant Religion, Engliſh Laws, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honeſt Countrymen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE deſign of this Book is twofold:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To give many and clear Demonſtrations, that King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was no ſuch Saint or Martyr as he has been commonly reputed, nor yet a true Proteſtant; but on the contrary, a great favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of Papiſts, and an oppreſſive Tyrant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To vindicate the juſt Reſiſtance the Parliament of 1640, and People, were conſtrain'd for their own ſafety to make.</p>
            <p>I foreſee this Treatiſe will meet with two Objections, Firſt, That it contradicts the old Maxim, <hi>De mortuis nihil niſi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> The ſecond, That it treats a crowned Head (nay, a pious Martyr's too) with little reſpect.</p>
            <p>To the firſt I anſwer, That <hi>bonum</hi> here muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>quaſi verum,</hi> that is, do not wrong or belie the Dead, for they are not in being to juſtify their own Innocency: otherwiſe it will not only reflect on profane but ſacred Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, nothing being more common in both, than to record the evil Actions even of Princes themſelves. I find this Maxim ſometimes highly inſiſted on by ſome of our Clergy and Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, eſpecially in favour of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. At other times theſe ſort of men make not the leaſt ſcruple (for ſiniſter ends) moſt unjuſtly to vilify, as the greateſt Villains imaginable, the Parliament of 1640, and thoſe worthy Patriots that join'd with it, to prevent the then many apparent inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Popery and Arbitrary Power, that King, his Queen, and evil Counſellors were bringing on the three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, of reſpecting this crowned Head, I muſt confeſs I have not treated him as I would a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100997:3"/>for the good of his People according to Law, but as a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> who cannot pretend to the leaſt Love or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from any of his Subjects; except thoſe Papiſts and others that were his Favorites, and were embarked in the ſame wicked Deſigns with him, eſteem it a great Sin to ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize and deify the beſt Magiſtrate on Earth, but a much greater, to adore a bloody and tyrannical Oppreſſor. And if the ſame men will, through cuſtom, ſimplicity, or want of information, no otherwiſe conſider Kings than in the gaudy name of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and admire them and their doings, as if they breathed not the ſame Breath with other mortal men, I thank God I have learnt better; and plainly ſee with what a beſotted and degenerated baſeneſs of ſpirit, imbaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tardized from the antient nobleneſs of their Anceſtors, they have not only in a religious, but a civil kind of Idolatry, idoliz'd this King, and ador'd the Image and Memory of him, who hath offered at more cunning fetches to undermine the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and put Tyranny into an Art, than any <hi>Britiſh</hi> King before him.</p>
            <p>To make good my Charge againſt this Prince, I ſhall firſt prove, that the general courſe of his Actions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly inconſiſtent with what a <hi>Saint</hi> doth, and ought to do: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. He was a proud <hi>Nimrod,</hi> a hardened <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> 2. A great <hi>Liar,</hi> (if he writ the Book call'd <hi>Eicon Baſilike</hi>) for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the many falſe Aſſertions againſt, and Accuſations of the Parliament, he begins with this notorious one, <hi>viz.</hi> That he call'd this laſt Parliament, not more by the advice of others, than his own choice and inclination; when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary was well known, both by the current of his own Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by the Favorites about him. For further proof of this, let any unbiaſſed Perſon but read his Promiſes, Oaths, Proteſtations, and ſolemn Declarations to the Parliament, and conſider how little of truth was in them, how the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in many of their Petitions charged him with the breach of them, and he will receive ſufficient ſatisfaction. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He unhallowed, and unchriſtianed the very Duty of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100997:3"/>Prayer it ſelf, by borrowing to a Chriſtian uſe, Prayers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to a Heathen God. What little fear had he of the true all ſeeing Deity? what little reverence of the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe Office is to dictate and preſent our Chriſtian Prayers? What little care of Truth in his laſt words, or honour to himſelf or to his <hi>Friends,</hi> or ſenſe of his Afflictions, or of that ſad hour which was upon him, as immediately before his death, to pop into the hand of that grave Biſhop who attended him, as a ſpecial Relick of his ſaintly Exerciſes, a Prayer ſtolen, word for word, from the mouth of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Woman praying to a Heathen God; and that in no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Book, but a vain amatorious Poem of Sir <hi>Philip Sidney</hi>'s <hi>Arcadia,</hi> a Book in that kind full of Worth and Wit, but among religious Thoughts and Duties not worthy to be named, nor read at any time without caution, much leſs in time of trouble and affliction to be a Chriſtian's Prayer-Book; that thought no better of the living God, than of a buzzard Idol, by ſerving him with the polluted traſh of Romances and Arcadia's: A bold and irreligious affront to the Divine Being! And in the 5th Chapter about Triennial Parliaments, he hath this paſſage, That <hi>the Tumults threatned to abuſe all Acts of Grace, and turn them into Wantonneſs.</hi> If they had turn'd his Wantonneſs into the Grace of not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Scripture, it had been well; this no ways became ſuch a Saint as they would make him. <hi>Herod</hi> was eaten up of Worms, for ſuffering others to compare his Voice to the Voice of God: But the borrower of this phraſe gives much more cauſe of jealouſy, that he likened his own <hi>Acts of Grace,</hi> to the <hi>Acts of God's Grace:</hi> And in the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his <hi>letting ſome men go up to the Pinacle of the Temple, was to caſt him down headlong.</hi> In this Simily we have himſelf compared to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> to the <hi>Devil;</hi> and his giving them that Act of ſettling, to his letting them go up to the Pinacle of the Temple: this was a goodly uſe made of Scripture in his ſolitudes! And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. on his repulſe at <hi>Hull,</hi> in his Prayer, thus, <hi>Let not thy Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100997:4"/>prevent the Objects and Opportunities of my Mercy.</hi> Muſt this be imputed to his Folly, or Blaſphemy, or to both? Shall the Juſtice of God give place, and ſerve to glorify the Mercies of a Man? All other men that know what they ask, deſire of God that their doings may tend to his Glory; But in this Prayer, God is required that his Juſtice would forbear to prevent, and as good as ſaid to intrench upon the Glory of a Man's Mercy. If God forbear his Juſtice, it muſt be, ſure, to the magnifying his own Mercy; but here a mortal Man takes the boldneſs to ask that Glory out of his hand. He hated all thoſe that were eſteemed Religious, doubting that their Principles too much aſſerted Liberty; this was plainly ſeen by his vehement proſecution of them. He took a moſt bloody and treacherous advantage of the Parliament's Army near <hi>Colebrook,</hi> whilſt he was under Treaty at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg</hi> with them, as he proteſted, to prevent the ſhedding of Blood. From the beginning of the War he would rather ſacrifice the Lives of thouſands of his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, than deliver up thoſe evil Counſellors that ſought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave <hi>England,</hi> or govern according to Law himſelf. He admired, encouraged, and protected none but the worſt and corrupteſt ſort of Courtiers; and the ragged Infantry of Stews and Brothels, the ſpawn and ſhipwrack of Taverns and Dicing-houſes, were the Bravo's and Hackſters that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him when he went in the moſt arbitrary and illegal manner into the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> and that in his Army he had 1000 of blaſpheming <hi>Cavaliers</hi> about him, whoſe mouths let fly Oaths and Curſes by the Volly; that entertain'd and encouraged a moſt ignorant, profane and vicious Clergy, learned in nothing but their Pride, their Covetouſneſs and Superſtition, whoſe unſincere and levenous Doctrines cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the People, firſt taught them Looſeneſs, then Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, looſning them from all ſound Knowledg and ſtrictneſs of Life, the more to fit them for the bondage of Tyranny and Superſtition: A Clergy that from the Preſs and Pulpit poiſoned the People with the following abominable enſlav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100997:4"/>Doctrines, of Paſſive (or more properly Aſſive) Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Non-reſiſtance, Obeying without Reſerve; That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> (by being anointed Birds) are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely unaccountable to the People: That they have a power over the Lives, Liberties, Laws and Goods of their people, and may do what they will with them: That the King can do no wrong, and many more ſuch horrid Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; enough to corrupt the beſt Prince, and enſlave the freeſt people.</p>
            <p>Theſe deviliſh enſlaving Doctrines, are moſt prejudicial and ungrateful to any people, that not only believe, but know, that they are Free-born Subjects: That all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was originally in the People, for they were before Kings: That all Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> came by their power, <hi>Ex Pacto aut Scelere,</hi> either by Compact, Covenant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the People, or by Uſurpation. That they did not like the <hi>Beaſts</hi> in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Viſion, <hi>drop down from Heaven,</hi> with all their Dignities, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but had their Root and Foundation from the Earth. If by Uſurpation, the longeſt Sword muſt decide the Controverſy; but if by Compact, the People of <hi>England</hi> cannot harbour ſuch hard thoughts of their Anceſtors, as to imagine they would make ſuch ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, fooliſh and nonſenſical Bargains, as to ſell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (and as far as in them lay) their poor Poſterity (for I may then with reaſon call them ſo) to a vile, miſerable and laſting Slavery. That if their Anceſtors were ſuch Fools, Knaves or Madmen to ſell their Birthrights, as <hi>Eſau</hi> did; the people of <hi>England</hi> know better things than to ſtand to that blind Bargain, it being againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which teaches Self-preſervation. Neither will the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible part of Mankind any more believe, that any Kings have ſuch a Divine Right as will juſtifie their violating their Coronation Oaths, breaking through all the Laws of the Land, that are the Peoples chiefeſt ſecurity: for they know and will preſerve the undoubted privileges of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Engliſh Men.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100997:5"/>
            <p>They are alſo well aſſured, that when a King or Prince ceaſes to govern according to Law, he <hi>turns Tyrant,</hi> and therefore ceaſes to be King, by which, as the <hi>Scots</hi> wiſely call it, <hi>he forefaults his Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Salus populi eſt ſuprema Lex;</hi> That the King was made for the Kingdom, and not the Kingdom for him. That the King doth not maintain the Kingdom, but the Kingdom the King. That the King and all Magiſtrates are the Kingdoms Miniſters and Servants. That it is their Duty and Glory to ſerve the Kingdom. That Kings muſt not reign by their Kingdoms ruin, nor be lifted up by their downfal. That the End is greater than the Means, Health better than Phyſick. That the King was not advanced to debaſe and enſlave his People. That it is not the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God that millions of men ſhould be miſerable ſlaves and vaſſals to One. That if the King be God's Anointed <hi>Jure Perſonae,</hi> in the Right of his Perſon, he is Man's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Jure Coronae,</hi> in Right of the Crown; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tho' he is above every one ſingly, yet not above <hi>All.</hi> For common ſafety is the ſole Sovereign.</p>
            <p>That if a King accepts of the Dignity of Government, and by his Coronation Oath or otherwiſe covenants with his People; he muſt ſubmit to all ſuch Agreements, to the Rules, Burdens and Troubles thereof. That the end of the King's Revenue was not to make him able to deſtroy, but preſerve his Subjects.</p>
            <p>That the King hath no Council above his Parliament. That the fooliſh ſenſleſs and wicked Doctrines of Paſſive O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Non-reſiſtance, if ſtrictly obſerved, are of dangerous conſequence to any Nation: for by theſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Poſitions, the Peoples hands being tied up, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Prayers and Tears left, <hi>One</hi> Armed Tyrant may (if he pleaſeth) deſtroy all his Subjects, and they like madmen be acceſſory to their own deaths. Surely none but Turks, Slaves, or French Vaſſals can really admire, or approve of ſuch an Obedience.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100997:5"/>
            <p>That <hi>Bracton</hi> and <hi>Fleta</hi> (who were eminent Lawyers) were in the right in declaring, That <hi>Rex Angliae habet ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> viz. <hi>Legem per quam factus eſt Rex, ac Comites &amp; Barones qui debent ei Fraenum ponere.</hi> The King of <hi>England</hi> hath for his Superiors both the Law, by which he is conſtituted King (and which is the meaſuring of his governing Power) and the Parliament, which is to reſtrain him if he do amiſs. <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Fleta l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>That the King by his Coronation Oath hath a power to rule his People for their beſt advantage, to adminiſter to every man his juſt rights, to confirm ſuch Laws that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make, conducing to the Common Good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And no other Authority can he with juſtice claim.</p>
            <p>That it is againſt the Moral Law, that a Kingdom ſhould ſuffer it ſelf to be unkingdom'd, ruin'd and deſtroy'd (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving power in their hands to ſave themſelves) ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being natural, even to brute beaſts when diſturbed.</p>
            <p>That God doth ſometimes require that <hi>One ſhould ſuffer for all,</hi> but never that <hi>All</hi> ſhould ſuffer for <hi>One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Rebellion conſiſts in reſiſting of juſt Governors in their juſt Government, and not in defending legal rights againſt a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>That it is unlawful to keep any Oaths, Vows and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to or for the King, that are againſt the good of the Kingdom; for the performing or keeping them would be an adding ſin unto ſin, wickedneſs unto wickedneſs, that is, to <hi>do Evil,</hi> as well as to promiſe the doing thereof. He that covenants to do things unlawful, covenants with Hell; muſt therefore the League of Hell and Death be maintained? Theſe things one would think ſhould have ſome weight with our Nonſwearing <hi>Jacobites,</hi> who chooſe rather to break the ſolemn Oaths they took to feed their Flocks, than to comply with ſwearing Faith and true Allegiance to that Prince, that Providence in a moſt miraculous manner raiſed up to deliver theſe Three Kingdoms from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſlavery it groaned under. A Prince who by his own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100997:6"/>and the Peoples Election can juſtly claim the beſt Title that ever any King of <hi>England</hi> had, let the Fools and Knaves who madly dote on the Divine Right of Succeſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſay what they will to the contrary.</p>
            <p>That the Oath of Allegiance is not made to the King <hi>Warring,</hi> or any ways <hi>Acting</hi> againſt the welfare of the Kingdom, but to him as Governing for good according to the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>That the Oath of Supremacy doth not allow him to be the Supreme Legiſlative Power of the Kingdom, and that he is in all Caſes the ſole Judg, and over all perſons an abſolute Lord, unto whoſe Will and Pleaſure the People are bound to be ſubject Actively or Paſſively; for ſuch a Power becometh only thoſe that are perfect as God himſelf is perfect.</p>
            <p>That all Oaths, Vows, Covenants and Compacts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, are conditional, reciprocal and mutual, the King being as well bound to the People as the People to the King.</p>
            <p>That the King's voluntary and plenary breach of his Agreement with the People, doth <hi>ipſo facto</hi> diſcharge the People from their Vows and Covenants, until ſuch time as the Agreement and Compact between the King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be again renewed, and united. The Nobility, Gentry and Clergy have in their noble aſſiſtance in the late Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution juſtified this Poſition to the height, and alſo that Kings are accountable to their Subjects for their Male Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration.</p>
            <p>That the People of <hi>England</hi> cannot give the Parliament a power to enſlave themſelves, for thereby they would be Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betrayers, and in a degree Self murderers. Neither can the People <hi>de Jure</hi> make Laws deſtructive to the Common-ſafety, or give any Power to others to the making of ſuch Laws.</p>
            <p>That what King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt told the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the Year 1609. is certainly true, viz. <hi>That he is no King but a Tyrant that governs not by Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100997:6"/>
            <p>That there is a very great and dangerous defect in the conſtitution of the Government of <hi>England,</hi> if the ſame Power that gave the Coronation Oath, cannot judg whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſaid Oath be kept or not, and call to an account for the violation thereof. <hi>Bracton, Fleta,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> of 1640. and the late <hi>Revolution</hi> ſeem clearly to allow Kings being accountable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Kings and all Magiſtrates ought to be Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not Bloody Tyrants to make their People miſerable, to reward Virtue, and not to encourage Injuſtice, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Vice. That if they would anſwer the end of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which is the Publick Good, they ought to ſtudy the happineſs and welfare of their Subjects equally with their Own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That if they will not govern thus according to Law and Juſtice, they muſt not think the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will be ſuch Fools as to ſtay for their accounting in the other World; for they do not love the <hi>Welſhmans</hi> reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which was <hi>to let her alone till the laſt Judgment, and then her would account fairly for all her Rogueries,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I am very well ſatisfied (let the wretched Advocates for Tyranny and Arbitrary Power ſay what they will to the contrary) That theſe Doctrines or Maxims cannot deſtroy Government, becauſe they will not permit Governors to deſtroy the People. Nay, they will eſtabliſh a Juſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by rooting out the Unjuſt. The Throne will be eſtabliſhed by Righteouſneſs, but ruined by Wickedneſs. Thoſe Doctrines that rectifie Governors in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Common Right and Juſtice, do faſten the Crowns of Government upon their Heads; for by doing every man right, their Throne is ſet up in every man's Heart: and not only ſo, but the <hi>promiſed Preſence of an Infinite Power, will ever ſecure and proſper ſuch Adminiſtrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe pious Doctrines do not implead Government, but the Evils thereof, and are all included in this, <hi>The Safety of the People is ſtill the chiefeſt Lord, Rule, Reaſon and Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100997:7"/>
            <p>Theſe Divine Truths will, I hope, be highly acceptable in this age of light and knowledge; tho <hi>Laud, Sibthorp, Manwaring, Mountague,</hi> and other wicked Clergy-men of thoſe and later times have unjuſtly eſteemed them Rebellious.</p>
            <p>I could produce many more Inſtances to inform the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded part of mankind, that this adored Prince was far from being a pious One; but for the preſent ſhall give but one more clear Demonſtration, that is, His cauſing a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be publiſhed and read in all Churches, that <hi>all Sports,</hi> &amp;c. whatſoever, were lawful on the <hi>Sabbath-day.</hi> How agreeable this moſt wicked Act can be to Religion I cannot conceive, and I am of opinion it will puzle all thoſe that in a blaſphemous ſtrain call him a Saint and Martyr to defend him from this horrid impiety. See the Declaration at large printed in the Book called <hi>A Vindication of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of</hi> 1640. Neither can I ſee for what Reaſons any of his adorers can make him a <hi>Martyr;</hi> for the word <hi>Martyr,</hi> in the Greek <hi>Martur,</hi> ſignifies <hi>Teſtis,</hi> a Witneſs, <hi>In Eccleſia dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Teſtis &amp; Confeſſor Veritatis Verbo Dei patefactae, ſingulariter autem ille, qui propter Confeſſionem Evangelicae veritatis ſuſtinet Afflictiones, ipſamque adeo Mortem.</hi> Our pretended Martyr (God knows) cannot come under any one of theſe Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters; for it is plain that he did not dye for being a Witneſs or Confeſſor of the Revealed Truths in God's Word, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he ſuffer Afflictions even unto Death for the ſake of owning or profeſſing Evangelical Truths: No, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament did not oppoſe or proſecute him for being a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, but for favouring Papiſts, and ſubverting in a moſt arbitrary manner all the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now proceed to ſhew that this King could not be a firm Proteſtant: His Letter to the Pope (printed at large in the Book called <hi>A Defence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640. <hi>and the People of</hi> England, <hi>againſt King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt and his Adherents</hi>) in anſwer to the Letter he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Pope, is enough to ſtartle any (but ſuch as <hi>Land</hi>'s) Proteſtants. He calls the Pope <hi>Most Holy Father,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100997:7"/>and tells him, <hi>I ſhall never be ſo extreamly affected to any thing in the World as to endeavour an Alliance with a Prince that hath the ſame apprehenſion of the True Religion with my ſelf.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> hath it in theſe words, <hi>Your Holineſſes Conjecture of Our Deſire to contract an Alliance and Marriage with a Catholick Family and Princeſs, is agreeable both to your Wiſdom and Charity; for we would never deſire ſo vehemently to be joind in a ſtrict and indiſſoluble Bond, with any mortal whatſoever, whoſe Religion we hated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And towards the end of the Letter, <hi>I entreat your Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to believe, that I have been always very far from encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Novelties, or to be a Partiſan of any Faction, againſt the Catholick Apoſtolick Roman Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In another place he proteſted, <hi>That he would expoſe Life and Eſtate in the Exaltation of the Holy Chair.</hi> This cannot redound to the honour of a Proteſtant King; for the <hi>Holy Chair,</hi> in its proper ſenſe, means nothing but down-right Popery.</p>
            <p>In another place he tells the Pope, <hi>I will employ my ſelf</hi> for the time to come, <hi>to have but one Religion, and one Faith, —Having reſolved in my ſelf to ſpare nothing in the World, and to ſuffer all manner of Diſcommodities, even to the hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Eſtate and Life for a thing ſo pleaſing to God.</hi> This Reſolution cannot look like his converting the Pope and others to the Proteſtant Religion, but directly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And in his Reply to the Nuncio upon his delivering the Popes Letter to him, which you may read in <hi>Cabala,</hi> or <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> pag. 214. he ſays,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I kiſs his Holineſs Feet, for the Favour and Honour he doth me; ſo much the more eſteemed, by how much the leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of me hitherto; and his Holineſs ſhall ſee what I do hereafter.</hi> [And ſo did <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the whole world; His Biſhops and Chaplains preſſed Popiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, and preached Doctrines of groſs Popery.] <hi>And I think my Father will do the like; ſo that his Holineſs ſhall not repent him of what he has done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His marrying a violent Papiſt, and making Articles with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100997:8"/>
               <hi>France</hi> in favour of Papiſts, (read his Articles at large in the Book called <hi>A Defence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) His ſtopping all Proſecution againſt them; His preferring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them to places of eminent Truſts, particularly <hi>Weſton</hi> to be his Lord Treaſurer, <hi>Arundell, Weſton, Gottington</hi> and <hi>Windebanck,</hi> who all died Papiſts; His pardoning <hi>Mountague</hi> his Chaplain for preaching down-right Popery; His un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful correſponding and conſpiring with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> to land Forces againſt the Parliament. He was kind to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts: And in his third year, againſt the plain advice of Parliament, like a kind Pope, ſold them many Indulgences for money. Adviſed with them on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, admitted them to private Conſultations with him and his Queen. His ſending one <hi>Dillon,</hi> a Papiſt Lord, ſoon after a chief Rebel, with Letters into <hi>Ireland;</hi> and his diſpatching a Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>Scotland</hi> (at that time in his own Cuſtody) that they ſhould <hi>forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as formerly had been agreed, cauſe all the</hi> Iriſh <hi>to riſe in Arms.</hi> Read the Commiſſion at large in the Book be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned. His cauſing ten thouſand Popiſh <hi>Iriſh</hi> Soldiers to be ordered for <hi>England</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Glamorgan,</hi> do all ſhew he had more confidence in <hi>Popiſh Iriſh,</hi> than in his <hi>Proteſtant Engliſh Subjects:</hi> A rare Proteſtant I profeſs. Theſe with his betraying the Proteſtants of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> Iſle of <hi>Rhee</hi> and <hi>Rochel,</hi> and the poor Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the number of 154000, ſhew the ſlender affection he had for the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> either at home or abroad. From ſuch a <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs Proteſtant,</hi> Good Lord for ever deliver theſe Kingdoms. Read his Letters to the <hi>Rochellers,</hi> and their Remonſtrance upon his betraying them, both printed in the Book, called <hi>A Defence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640. and you will have little cauſe to admire this Martyr; And alſo the Sheet called, <hi>Murder will out,</hi> printed in the ſame Book, which makes it appear he had a hand in the horrid <hi>Iriſh Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall plainly make it appear, beyond all doubt, that this <hi>King</hi> was an <hi>oppreſſive Tyrant;</hi> and ſhould
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100997:8"/>I proceed on this melancholy Subject ſo largely, as with the greateſt truth and matters of Fact I might, I ſhould have cauſe to cry out with the Poet, <hi>Tantae molis erat Romanam condere gentem.</hi> Many Inſtances of his Arbitrary and Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Government being printed in the Book called, <hi>A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640, &amp;c. and alſo the following Papers, which ſet this King out to the life, <hi>viz. The Pope's Letter to King</hi> Charles <hi>I.</hi> and <hi>King</hi> Charles<hi>'s Anſwer. His Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Marriage with</hi> France. <hi>His Declaration of Sports on the Lord's Day. His Letters of Aſſurance to the Proteſtants of</hi> Rochel; and <hi>their Remonſtrance on his deceiving them. His Commiſſion to the Iriſh Rebels: and</hi> Rorie Macquire <hi>and</hi> Philem Oneal<hi>'s Declaration thereupon. K.</hi> Charles <hi>II. Letter to the Court of Claims in</hi> Ireland, <hi>in behalf of the Marqueſs of</hi> Antrim, <hi>for acting by King</hi> Charles <hi>I. Order. King</hi> Charles<hi>'s Prayer taken out of</hi> Pembrook<hi>'s</hi> Arcadia. <hi>An Abridgment of the Articles of Peace that King</hi> Charles <hi>I. made with the Iriſh Rebels. Lord</hi> Angleſey<hi>'s Memorandum, and</hi> Walker<hi>'s Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt</hi> Eikon Baſilike.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now content my ſelf with enumerating a few more Inſtances of his grievous oppreſſing the People of <hi>England</hi> as a Tyrant: <hi>viz.</hi> By his raiſing, without Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 200000 <hi>l.</hi> on the poor Merchants for Ship-money, Coat and Conduct money. His great <hi>Minions</hi> and <hi>Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> inventing new methods of Monopolies, without ever acquainting the Parliament, to enable him, in a full time of Peace, to live without a Parliament, as he did about 11 Years together; Compulſive Knighthoods; the ſeizing, not of one <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard, but of whole Inheritances, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Foreſt, or Crown-lands; Corruption and Bribery compounded for, with Impunities granted for the future: Arbitrary and exceſſive Fines on thoſe People that ſtood in the gap againſt his <hi>Tyranny;</hi> beſides the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Slaſhings, Whippings, Pillorings, and horrible Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments for many years. His intending to bow or break his People, to perſwade or force them to ſlavery, is ſo clear
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100997:9"/>by the whole courſe of his Reign, that 'tis amazing that men (even of the higheſt ſtamp of <hi>Toryiſm</hi>) ſhould have Front enough to deny it. He turn'd the Lord <hi>Conway</hi> out of his Secretary's place, becauſe he would not make the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary advances to <hi>Rome,</hi> but refuſed to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Henry</hi> VII's Chappel, after Popiſh <hi>Laud</hi>'s way, which was not <hi>in Bread,</hi> but <hi>in Wafers.</hi> His undermining our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Government; his raiſing an Army of <hi>Engliſh, Scots, Germans,</hi> and bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, to ſubject his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Fortunes to his Will and Power, and make good the Breaches upon the Liberties of <hi>England.</hi> That never was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Parliaments, nor to call them, but for a greedy hope of a whole National Bribe, his <hi>Subſidies;</hi> and never loved, never fulfil'd, never promoted the true End of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Redreſs of Grievances, but ſtill put them off and prolonged them, whether gratified or not gratified. That cauſed Court Letters and Intimations to be ſent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the People from their free electing the beſt affected to their Religion and Countries Liberties. That could not forbear declaring, that <hi>the execution of</hi> Strafford <hi>ſtung his Conſcience;</hi> and no marvel, when he was the chief Author of thoſe Miſdeeds he ſuffered for. This <hi>Stafford</hi> was one of the boldeſt and moſt impetuous Inſtruments that the King had, to advance any violent or illegal Deſign. He had ruled <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>England,</hi> in an arbitrary manner; he had endeavoured to ſubvert the Fundamental Laws, to ſubvert Parliaments, and incenſe the King againſt them. He had endeavoured to make Hoſtility between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> he had counſel'd the King to call o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army of Papiſts which he had cunningly raiſed to reduce <hi>England,</hi> as appear'd by good teſtimony then preſent at the Conſultation. For which and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Crimes proved againſt him in 28 <hi>Articles,</hi> he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of High-Treaſon by the Parliament. This pious Martyr could highly demonſtrate his remorſe for the <hi>Blood of Strafford</hi> that all good Men acquitted him of, but not the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100997:9"/>
               <hi>leaſt ſorrow for ſetting up his Standard, and cauſing a Sea of innocent Blood to be ſpilt by the Civil War, occaſion'd by his Male Adminiſtration.</hi> That according to his own confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, violated the Privileges of the Commons, by going in an Arbitrary way into their Houſe. That as his Cabinet Letters declare, call'd them <hi>a mungrel Parliament, that vext his Queen with their baſe and mutinous Motions.</hi> A ſpecial Bargain of ſuch a <hi>Queen,</hi> at whoſe landing at <hi>Dover,</hi> the 25th of <hi>June</hi> (New-ſtile) 1625, the <hi>Sun</hi> withdrew its Beams, as being unwilling to ſhine upon a Deſcent ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fatal to this Nation, and the Night hid the Miſeries which that Day were brought into this flouriſhing Iſland upon her arrival.</p>
            <p>On the 26th the <hi>Queen</hi> with the <hi>King</hi> made their entry to <hi>London,</hi> having among others in her Train, <hi>A Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Biſhop, on whom King</hi> Charles <hi>was obliged to ſettle a Penſion of</hi> 4000 <hi>l. a Year. Four Abbots under the Title of</hi> Almoners, <hi>on each a</hi> 1000 <hi>l. Two Chaplains Prieſts</hi> 1400 <hi>l. Two Clerks of the Chappel; two Grooms: Moreover,</hi> 12 <hi>Prieſts of the Oratory, on whom</hi> 6000 <hi>l. were to be ſettled for their ſubſistence and maintenance.</hi> But beſides all the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Perſons, the <hi>Queen,</hi> not to truſt to Proteſtants, brought over with her a Train of Roman Catholicks, whereof ſhe form'd her Houſe, and, as it after prov'd, a Seminary in the Kingdom; four Ladies of Honour for her Bedchamber, ſix Ladies of Honour with their Governante, and one under her, beſides Servants; 18 Gentlemen, ſix <hi>Valets de Chambre,</hi> a Chamberlain, a Secretary, five Chambermaids, Semſtreſſes, Laundreſles, a Phyſician, an Apothecary, Chirurgions, a Pantler, Cup-bearers, Cooks, Potagers, Roaſters, Bakers, Stewards, Coachmen, and all the Officers of her Stables. At her coming up to <hi>London,</hi> almoſt all the People of that great City went before her (juſt as heretofore the Trojans did the Horſe that was the cauſe of their deſtruction) in triumph into their City, with demonſtrations of joy. But to their great ſorrow, theſe Halcion days laſted but a ſhort
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100997:10"/>time, for they ſoon found the Queen's numerous Train of Eccleſiaſticks cauſed no ſmall clamours and murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the People all over the Kingdom; for theſe Vipers were in perpetual motion, and continually running from Houſe to Houſe under pretence of Converſion-work; openly boaſting they had already converted many thouſands in the little time they had been in <hi>England.</hi> Whereupon the King received divers Complaints, as well from Proteſtant Biſhops and Miniſters, as from the Maſters of Families, who accuſed thoſe Prieſts, not only of perverting their Servants, but their Children; and that by their wicked inſtigation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to their Parents, ſeveral of them were gone away beyond Sea, to be put into Colleges and Convents, for their more commodious being bred up in the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: But upon all matters that happened as to that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the Queen ſtill ſtept into the Breach, to prevent by her Credit any Miſchiefs that ſhould have fallen on the Prieſts. But the Complaints of the People againſt theſe Vermin the Queen brought with her were ſo great, that the King was neceſſitated to ſend them back into <hi>France;</hi> which was done in <hi>Auguſt</hi> the ſame Year he was crown'd. But at the ſame time to prevent their complaining, the <hi>King</hi> heaped Favours, Benevolences and Preſent upon all the Fry of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, to reward their labour of the Tares they had ſown and left behind them in <hi>England:</hi> However all this Liberality of the King was not ſufficient to hinder their Complaints, nor their Sollicitations in the Court of <hi>France</hi> to return into <hi>England,</hi> to gather (as they ſaid) the Fruits of their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. The <hi>Queen</hi> on the other hand ſaw her ſelf foreſtall'd of her deſire to propagate the Catholic Faith, eſpecially in her Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> and being puſh'd on by her Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and others of the ſame brood, did not fail to write of this matter very ſmartly to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. her Brother, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to the <hi>Queen Mother.</hi> And the King of <hi>France</hi> being puſhed on by the Queen Mother, took as a very great and ſenſible Affront, the ſending back of all the <hi>French</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100997:10"/>that belonged to the Retinue, and were the Domeſtick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Queen his Siſter. The Cardinal that was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Governour of the King, was ſo angry to ſee the <hi>French</hi> returned, (for that grievouſly broke his Meaſures in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) and prevailed ſo much on the King his Maſter, that he got him to ſend over an Embaſſador Extraordinary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with the Queen, and to make his complaints of it to the King. And that Miniſter did his buſineſs ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that thoſe who had been diſmiſſed, and obliged to leave the Kingdom, return'd to their former Poſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Queen, their Miſtreſs, and began their old trade of perverting people to the Romiſh Religion; which laſted as long as the Queen continued in <hi>England.</hi> Whilſt the King was thus govern'd by his <hi>Papiſt Queen</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> how could <hi>poor England</hi> think of being happy, or free from <hi>Popery,</hi> and its natural Conſequence <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That inſtead of praying for his <hi>People,</hi> as a good King ſhould do, he pray'd to be delivered from them, as from wild Beaſts, Inundations, and raging Seas, that had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born all Loyalty, (that is, would not let him be according to his Will, a great Tyrant) Modeſty, Laws, Juſtice and Religion: God ſave the People from ſuch Interceſſors.</p>
            <p>That the petitioning for removal of Evil Counſellors, and redreſſing Grievances in Church and State, was to him an intolerable Oppreſſion. His ſending an Agent to <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> with Letters to that King, requiring Aid againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> beſides the 8000 <hi>Iriſh</hi> raiſed by <hi>Strafford,</hi> which with a <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Army were to join the <hi>Engliſh</hi> he then had. He encouraged the <hi>Scots</hi> by telling them, what Money and Horſe he was to have from <hi>Denmark;</hi> yielding to the hireling Army of <hi>Scotland,</hi> rather than to the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Requeſts of his Parliament. His ſtopping and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying, both by Sea and Land, to his utmoſt power, thoſe Proviſions and Supplies which the Parliament ſent to relieve
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100997:11"/>the miſerable <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> clearly demonſtrates he was deſirous of having them ſacrificed to his <hi>Iriſh Friends,</hi> who were bloody Cut-throats. <hi>Ireland</hi> being as <hi>Ephraim,</hi> the <hi>ſtrength of his Head; Scotland,</hi> as <hi>Judah,</hi> was his <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver;</hi> but over <hi>England,</hi> as over <hi>Edom,</hi> he meant to caſt his <hi>Shoe.</hi> His being ſo falſe in all his Treaties, as to follow his grand Maxim, <hi>viz. Always to put ſomething into his Treaties which might give</hi> colour <hi>to refuſe all that was in other things granted,</hi> and <hi>ſo make them ſignify nothing:</hi> a way of treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that no way became a Crown'd Head, much leſs an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt pious <hi>Prince,</hi> who ought to be ſincere in all his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</p>
            <p>That was ſo full of Revenge upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that he ſent his <hi>violent Queen</hi> (who with the greateſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs went) to <hi>Holland,</hi> where <hi>ſhe,</hi> by his order, <hi>pawn'd</hi> and ſet to ſale the <hi>Crown Jewels,</hi> (a Crime heretofore counted treaſonable) for no other uſe, but to raiſe an Army of Horſe and Foot, with Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a very pious Deſign to bring in a wicked parcel of Foreigners to cut his Engliſh Subjects Throats. This was a Martyr with a witneſs, by whom the Nation had been ſwallowed up with Blood and Ruin, had not his Strength fail'd him more than his Will. His admiring thoſe Miniſters that ſtrengthened his Hands, and hardened his Heart, and applauded him in his wilful ways againſt the Good of his People, to whom he was a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine.</hi> They were as dear and pleaſing to him, as <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> the Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> was to <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> for they had learnt not to propheſy againſt <hi>Bethel, for it is the King's Chappel, the King's Court:</hi> But his hating thoſe good and pious Miniſters the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſent him, proceeded from their telling him plain Truths, what was his Duty and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and preaching up Repentance for what he had done. His moſt wrongfully pretending that he muſt kill or be killed, is ſo notoriouſly falſe, that nothing can be clearer, it being very manifeſt that never was King leſs in danger of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100997:11"/>any violence from his Subjects, till he unſheath'd his Sword againſt them. Nay long after that time, when he had ſpilt the Blood of thouſands, they had ſtill his Perſon in a fooliſh veneration. His own Letters taken at the Battel of <hi>Naſeby</hi> were of great importance, to let the People ſee what Faith there was in all his Promiſes and ſolemn Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations: they diſcovered his good Affection to Papiſts and Iriſh Rebels; the ſtrict Intelligence he held; the perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and diſhonourable Peace he made with them; not ſollicited, but rather ſolliciting, which by all Invocations that were holy he had in publick abjured. See the Articles of Peace abridged, in <hi>the Defence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Letters revealed his Endeavours to bring in Foreign Forces, <hi>Iriſh, French, Dutch, Lorainers,</hi> and our old Invaders the <hi>Danes,</hi> upon <hi>England.</hi> Theſe were viſible to all men under his own hand, and were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the Parliament to be printed for publick Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Theſe his own Letters diſcovering his Grand Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iniquity, this holy Man was not a little concern'd at their being made publick; for they pull'd off his Mask, and ſhew'd the World what ſort of a Man he was.</p>
            <div type="defense_of_Parliament">
               <p>Having, I hope beyond all doubt, given clear Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations that King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt could be no Saint, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, nor a true Proteſtant; but on the contrary, a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of Popery, a wicked and oppreſſive Tyrant: I have little or no occaſion to proceed to my ſecond Propoſition, which was, to vindicate the <hi>Parliament</hi> of 1640, and all thoſe Noble Patriots that joined with it againſt that King and his Evil Counſellors; however I ſhall briefly defend them from the impudent Charge of Rebels, tho I am hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſorry that the ignorance of ſome, prejudice and ſelf-intereſt of others, ſhould give the leaſt occaſion for this Defence, eſpecially in theſe our days, when, God be praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Men can ſpeak and write Engliſh Truths without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100997:12"/>hang'd for them, as in the late wicked Reigns, when Villains declared it for Law, that <hi>Scribere</hi> was <hi>Agere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In proſecution of this Defence, I ſhall ſhew you,
<list>
                     <item>1. Who did riſe and oppoſe this Prince, and his Evil Counſellors.</item>
                     <item>2. What were the Reaſons that induced ſo great an Oppoſition.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Parliament and their Adherents, conſiſted of the beſt of the Nobility and Gentry, Men eminent for Piety and Juſtice, <hi>viz.</hi> The Earls of <hi>Bedford, Mancheſter,</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> &amp;c. Lords, <hi>Paget, Mandeville, Wharton, Hollis, Brook,</hi> &amp;c. Commoners, Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pymm,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> Sir <hi>John Elliot,</hi> Sir <hi>John Heveningham,</hi> Sir <hi>Nathaniel Barnardiſton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Strangeways,</hi> Sir <hi>William Earl,</hi> &amp;c. and many more too many to be herein mentioned. It was alſo evident, that the moſt worthy of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the Kingdom, did moſt heartily engage with them in this moſt Righteous Work of delivering <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and tho by Blood, yet God gave them ſucceſs againſt that Tyrant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For what Reaſons did the Parliament and People preſume to reſiſt the Lord's Anointed? I anſwer, let thoſe that deſire ſatisfaction in this point, but read over care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and impartially, this ſmall Book, and that called <hi>A Defence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they will have no cauſe to enquire further; ſo many real matters of Fact being therein contained, almoſt enough to convince even <hi>Thomas a Didimus.</hi> But to be ſhort, they were neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereunto, being in the greateſt danger of loſing the Proteſtant Religion, their Laws, their Lives and Liberties.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100997:12"/>Was it not high time to ſtand up, when all that was dear to Free-born <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> was at ſtake? Was not the King a great favourer of Papiſts, and lover of Tyranny? Was he not ruled by his violent Popiſh Queen, a wicked, corrupt and Arbitrary Nobility, Gentry and Clergy, many of them of mean fortunes, that were unhappy for Himſelf, but more unhappy for his Kingdom? And were ſuch perſons as theſe fit to be truſted by the people? Men that laboured all they could to make the King a powerful Tyrant, and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects a miſerable enſlaved people. Beſides, could rational men think it ſafe to permit ſuch a King, and his Evil Counſellors to carry on thoſe their Arbitrary Deſigns, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently deſtructive to the happineſs and welfare of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> If they had permitted theſe Evils to come upon them, they ought not only to be beg'd for Fools, or Madmen, but deſerved to loſe the privileges of a <hi>Free People.</hi> But God be praiſed for inſpiring and aſſiſting them with greater Wiſdom and Courage, than fooliſhly and tamely to ſuffer their Religion, Laws and Liberties to become a Sacrifice to that Tyrant, or his Crew. His governing <hi>ad Libitum Regis</hi> by his own arbitrary Luſt and Will, and not <hi>per Legem Terrae,</hi> and calling but <hi>three Parliaments</hi> in all his Reign, which (to the ſorrow of <hi>England</hi>) was almoſt twenty four years, muſt naturally create enemies againſt him. To conclude this Head: His whole Reign was ſuch a continued piece of Popiſh Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Oppreſſion, that the people of <hi>England</hi> with the greateſt chearfulneſs ran the hazard of their Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes to free themſelves and poſterity from them both: and I challenge the greateſt Advocates for this pretended Saint and Martyr, to diſprove the leaſt matter in this Book laid to his charge; nay, I'll go farther, I challenge them to give me, or any one elſe a ſatisfactory account of <hi>one good Act</hi> he ever did for the glory of God or the good of his three Kingdoms, except conſtrained by his people thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100997:13"/>
               <p>For a concluſion of this Diſcourſe, I ſhall make a few Remarques, which I hope, if well obſerved, may be very uſeful not only to this preſent age, but to poſterity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I ſhall give a ſhort Anſwer to this Queſtion, <hi>Why do the generality of the Clergy and Laity ſo much adore and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize all Monarchs</hi> (whether good or bad) <hi>above the People?</hi> The Reaſon is plain, The People have nothing material in a Monarchical Government to beſtow upon theſe <hi>Court Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites,</hi> for the Kings have the diſpoſal of the Biſhopricks, Deanaries, Prebendaries, Archdeaconries, and moſt other great Livings, and alſo moſt of the Temporal beneficial Places, as Chancellors, Judges and other great Offices; from ſuch a ſort of men as theſe nothing but Court-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines can be expected; for they are well aſſured, ſhould they preach or write for the Rights or Privileges of the People in Arbitrary Reigns, it would be the ready way to daſh all their hopes of preferment into pieces. And here I cannot but make a melancholy Obſervation, as to the Clergy in general of the late Reigns, <hi>viz.</hi> That by all I could hear or read, they have been ſo far from being Chriſtian Advocates for the Rights and Privileges of milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of people, that they have in a moſt wicked manner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted and preached up thoſe Doctrines that plainly tended to make them miſerable and laſting Slaves. Indeed I muſt confeſs ſome few of them have ſignalized themſelves for the good of the People, and againſt Popery. Particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that incomparable Phoenix of our Age, Mr. <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL JOHNSON,</hi> a perſon that by his ſenſible Converſation, and his golden Works, hath done more ſervice, to reſcue <hi>England</hi> from Popery and Slavery, and ſecure Engliſh mens Rights and Privileges, than moſt (if not all) the Biſhops and Clergy-men ever did ſince the Reformation. His Works are ſo excellent and highly valuable, that they will preſerve his Fame long after he is dead; and will make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100997:13"/>good that Motto, <hi>Vivit poſt funera virtus.</hi> And I could wiſh the Nobility and Gentry would encourage (by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions) ſome Bookſeller or Printer to reprint all this great Man's Works in one Folio; that the Divine and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Truths therein contained, might be handed down (for the publick good) to poſterity. I am extreamly well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that our Gracious King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> hath in ſome meaſure (tho not ſo much, nor ſo ſoon as I could wiſh, tho he had merited more than others) rewarded his inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſufferings and eminent ſervices for theſe Kingdoms. I would never have a good man have the leaſt cauſe to ſay, <hi>Virtus laudatur &amp; alget;</hi> and that
<q>
                     <l>Aude aliquid brevibus gyaris aut carcere dignum,</l>
                     <l>Si vis eſſe aliquid—</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Was the right way to preferment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What occaſions the Clergy's uſurping one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince more than belongs to them, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> when, God knows, they have work enough to preach the Goſpel as they ought to do, that their <hi>Flocks might be well fed with the Milk of God's Word?</hi> 1. Want of that true Piety that would keep them cloſer to their duties to God and men. 2. As I hinted before, they pick up ſcraps of Law to make Princes great, that they may get promotion thereby, tho to the ſacrificing of their Country. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The imprudent familiarity the Nobility and Gentry have with them, many of whom are poor, ignorant, impious and ſcandalous fellows, that ariſe from being Pariſh Boys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which makes them ſo proud as to ſtrut and lord it over the People to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious degree. I would by no means be thought by this, to be an enemy to pious good Clergy-men, that as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Miniſters diſcharge their duties; for I ſolemnly profeſs I have the higheſt value and eſteem for all ſuch holy men. And I obſerved in my Travels in <hi>Holland,</hi> that the <hi>Dutch</hi> did highly reſpect their Miniſters (whom I muſt really
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100997:14"/>confeſs, I believe to be famous for good Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, far beyond the generality of the <hi>Engliſh Clergy.</hi>) Yet they kept theſe good men at a due diſtance, not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of their Miniſters to be ſeen at any time in an Ale-houſe, Tavern, or in a Coffee-houſe, except on their Travels, where refreſhments muſt be had to ſupport na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And if any of them ſhall tranſgreſs in this matter, they immediately forfeit their reputation and eſteem with the people. And if they ſhould in their Pulpits preſume to meddle with State-affairs, and the Magiſtrates hear of it, they ſend them a pair of Shoos, and order them to be gone.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Mountague, Sybthorp</hi> and <hi>Manwaring,</hi> of old; <hi>Pelling, Sherlock, Cartwright, White, Lake, Watſon, Crew, Thompſon, Collier, Snet, Cook, Hawkins, Hicks, Wilſon, Long, Thomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of <hi>Briſtol, Hollingworth, Milbourn, Birch,</hi> and a great many more of the ſame ſtamp in the late Reigns, had been dealt with according to their deſerts, I know what would juſtly have become of moſt of them.</p>
               <p>'Tis obſerved, that the People of <hi>England</hi> are famous for puniſhing little Rogues, ſuch as <hi>Pick-pockets,</hi> &amp;c. but care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly and imprudently paſs by thoſe Clergymen and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers that have to the greateſt degree robb'd them of their undoubted Birthrights and greateſt Privileges, by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale, and endeavoured to eſtabliſh a Government over them as abſolute as the Grand Seignior's.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I ſhall take notice of the Obſervation of the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> in that ſolemn manner as now kept; and if I make ſome cloſe Remarks thereon, I hope I ſhall not be hardly thought on, ſince a Perſon in ſo high a ſtation, ſo eminent for Parts and Piety, as Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> hath, before a great Auditory in the famous City of <hi>London,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) expreſſed himſelf fully againſt the keeping up that day, in his Sermon preached at St. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100997:14"/>Church <hi>London,</hi> Jan. 30. 1680. and ſince printed by <hi>R. Chiſwell:</hi> His words are, <q rend="margQuotes">I acknowledg it were better if we could have <hi>Job</hi>'s Wiſh, that this day ſhould periſh, that darkneſs and the ſhadow of death ſhould cover it, that it ſhould not ſee the dawning of the day, nor ſhould the light ſhine upon it; it were better to ſtrike it out of our <hi>Kalendar,</hi> and make our <hi>January</hi> determine at the 29th, and add theſe remaining days to <hi>February.</hi> 
                  </q>And to put it out of doubt, what the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s meaning was in that expreſſion, <hi>It were better if we could have</hi> Job<hi>'s Wiſh,</hi> I ſhall quote ſome other expreſſions in that Sermon. <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. are theſe words; <q rend="margQuotes">Upon their loving Truth and Peace, thoſe black and mournful days ſhould be converted to days of gladneſs.</q> 
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. <q rend="margQuotes">It might have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that our 29th of <hi>May</hi> ſhould have worn out the remembrance of the 30th of <hi>January;</hi> and now at the end of two and thirty years, (to this time 50) it may be reaſonably asked, Should we ſtill continue to faſt and mourn? <hi>Pag.</hi> 28.</q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes"> [If we come to love the Truth and Peace] to live in Love and Peace one with another, then our days of Faſting ſhall be turn'd into ſolemn and chearful Feaſts: Then ſhall our 29th of <hi>May</hi> ſwallow up the remembrance of the 30th of <hi>January:</hi> Or perhaps, as the Prophet foretold ſuch happy Deliverances ſhould come to the Jews, as ſhould make even that out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to be forgotten; ſo we might hope for ſuch days as ſhould out ſhine and darken the very 29th of <hi>May</hi>—If we come to love Truth and Peace, then ſhall even this Faſt of the 10th month, according to the Jewiſh Account (which according to Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> is exactly our 30th of <hi>January</hi>) be to us Joy and Gladneſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I ſhall obſerve, That the keeping up the 30th of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> hath never, as I could learn, done the leaſt good, but much burt to theſe Kingdoms; for it hath given, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100997:15"/>ſtill gives the Clergy (who rarely preach or write for the good of the Kingdom) an opportunity of poiſoning the People with lying Stories, and dangerous Notions, many of them crying up this King (to the great ſcandal of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity) in a blaſphemous manner, venting ſuch horrid Expreſſions as theſe in his behalf, <hi>viz.</hi> THAT HIS BLOOD CRIED LOWDER FOR VENGEANCE, THAN THE BLOOD OF JESUS (our dear Redeemer.) Another vile Wretch ſaid, <hi>That they accuſed our Saviour of being a Winebibber, and a Friend of Publicans and Sinners, but could lay no ſuch Charge to the Martyr of their own making.</hi> Are ſuch wicked Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be tolerated among Chriſtians? God forbid.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Contrary to all Chriſtianity, it effectually keeps up perpetual Animoſities, Wraths, Feuds, and Diviſions, in theſe three Kingdoms. Which are of a pernicious conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the publick Welfare of any People. For what good Man can hear (without a juſt reſentment) his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors that ventured their <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> for the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their Country, be moſt falſly and wickedly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned as <hi>Rebels,</hi> by a parcel of Clergymen, generally Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates for Tyranny, and many of them little ſneaking, ignorant, and ſcandalous Fellows, who on this <hi>madding Day</hi> impudently vent their <hi>lying Harangues</hi> againſt them, who under God were the Inſtruments of much happineſs to <hi>England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The keeping up that day, furniſheth the <hi>Jacobites</hi> with a mighty Argument againſt the late happy and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Revolution; for they argue thus. Since by Act of Parliament, the oppoſers of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who acted by authority of Parliament (mark that) are brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Rebels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how much more are they Rebels, that againſt their own Principles of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Non Reſiſtance,</hi> turned out their <hi>Jure divino</hi> King, the late Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100997:15"/>
                  <hi>James,</hi> who had not committed half ſo many arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and illegal Actions, nor been guilty of ſuch notorious Violations upon the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> as that <hi>Holy Martyr Charles</hi> the Firſt was juſtly charged with?</p>
               <p n="4">4. This ſolemn obſervation is pleaſing or acceptable to none, but thoſe wicked Clergy-men or Laymen, that either had a hand in thoſe arbitrary doings of that King; or that would ſtill maintain and juſtifie ſuch pernicious Doctrines and Actions. Neither is it to be wondred at, that ſome of the Laymen are for keeping up this day; by reaſon thy now enjoy the Eſtates of thoſe men that aſſiſted in the redemption of their oppreſſed Country: for the old Saying is true, <hi>Intereſt may flatter, but it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. If againſt all reaſon and juſtice to the memory of our deceaſed Patriots, I ſhould <hi>pro confeſſo</hi> allow they had been Rebels by reſiſting this King, I would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſatisfied, what hath their innocent poſterity to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for in this caſe?</p>
               <p>To conclude all; I do ſolemnly profeſs and declare in the preſence of God, That I have not written this Book to vindicate the Actions of any Relations of mine that had any hand in oppoſing that King; nay I am not ſure any of my Family was engaged in that Righteous Cauſe; but for the undeceiving of thoſe that are moſt ſtrangely, againſt all truth and reaſon, deluded by the Clergy to believe a <hi>Lie, viz.</hi> That King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was a Saint and Martyr, and that all thoſe good people that withſtood his notorious op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and evil deſigns, were great <hi>Rebels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dear Country men, I have now ſet clear light before you, and I hope you will no longer walk in darkneſs; I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100997:16"/>deſire you will carefully read over and conſider this ſmall Book, and that called <hi>A Defence of the Parliament of</hi> 1640, which contains a black liſt of the pretended Martyr's ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical actions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon all occaſions ſtand u p for the undoubted Truths therein; by doing of which you will highly contribute towards the ſecuring to your ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and poſterity, a <hi>Laſting Happineſs:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Which is the moſt hearty prayer of yours and his Countries real Friend,</hi> D. J.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
